Chenhao Li | PhD

⊠ lichenhao.sg@gmail.com

Summary

An experienced computational biologist with strong passion for understanding biology through computational approaches. Proficient in mining, visualising, interpreting and modelling high-throughput sequencing data. Interested in a broad range of biological problems, especially understanding the dynamics of microbial communities.

Education

PhD in Computer Science

National University of Singapore

Jan 2015-Apr 2019

Thesis: Modelling Approaches to Predicting Microbial Interactions

Supervisors: Niranjan Nagarajan, Limsoon Wong

- Award for outstanding achievement 2018 (GIS Graduate Student Prize)
- Award for exellence in teaching 2018 (Honor List of Student Tutors)

BSc (Hon.) in Computational Biology

National University of Singapore

Aug 2010-Jun 2014

Cumulative Average Point: 4.7/5.0 (First Class Honours)

- o Best academic exercise in Computational Biology 2014 (Lijen Industrial Development Medal)
- Best student in Computer Science stream 2011 (Lim Soo Peng Book Prize)
- o Dean's List (2011/2012 Semester II and 2013/2014 Semester I)
- Full scholarship for Chinese students awarded by the Ministry of Education 2009 (SM3)

Work Experience

Research Fellow

Xavier lab at Massachusetts General Hospital

Dec 2020 – Present

- o affiliated with the Broad Institute and Harvard Medical School
- Analysis of single cell and spatial transcriptomics data of gut tissues
- Investigation of associations of gut microbiome and cardiovascular disease risks using multiomics data

Research Associate

Genome Institute of Singapore

Apr 2020 - Nov 2020

- Build and maintain bioinformatics infrastructure for COVID-19 sample analysis
- Lead bioinformatics analysis of skin metagenomics samples

Postdoctoral Fellow

Genome Institute of Singapore

Apr 2019 – *Mar* 2020

- Investigate antibiotics resistant bacteria in environmental samples
- o Build and maintain data handling system for nanopore sequencing data for the institute
- Predict ecological interactions between microbial species

Bioinformatics specialist

Genome Institute of Singapore

Jul 2014 – Mar 2019

- Mine association between disease and human microbiome
- Predict ecological interactions between microbial species
- o Design, optimise and maintain high-performance pipelines for sequencing data analysis
- Guide and train attachment students

Technical skills

Github page: https://github.com/lch14forever

- Proficient in R, Python and Linux bash scripting; experience with C, C++, MATLAB, JAVA,
 Perl, HTML, PHP and SCALA
- Extensive experience with bioinformatic pipeline frameworks (Nextflow, Snakemake, Bpipe), high performance computing environments (cluster, AWS), version control systems (git) and containers (docker)
- Experience with next-generation sequencing data (Shotgun metagenomics, amplicon sequencing, RNA-Seq, whole genome sequencing)

Software

- BEEM-static An R package for inferring microbial interactions based on Lotka-Volterra models from cross-sectional microbiome sequencing data. https://github.com/lch14forever/ BEEM-static
- 2. BEEM Estimating Lotka-Volterra models from time-course microbiome sequencing data. https://github.com/lch14forever/BEEM
- 3. shotgunmetagenomics-nf A reference-based pipeline for shotgun metagenomics. https://github.com/lch14forever/shotgunmetagenomics-nf
- 4. MicrobiomeViz An R package for visualising microbiome data. https://github.com/lch14forever/microbiomeViz
- 5. INC-Seq Analysis pipeline for accurate single molecule reads using nanopore sequencing. https://github.com/CSB5/INC-Seq

Publications (*: first author, #: correspondance author)

- C. Li**, T. V. Av-Shalom, J. W. G. Tan, J. S. Kwah, K. R. Chng, N. Nagarajan*. BEEM-Static: Accurate inference of ecological interactions from cross-sectional metagenomic data. PLOS Computational Biology. (2021).
- 2. A global metagenomic map of urban microbiomes and antimicrobial resistance. **Cell**. (2021). (MetaSUB consortium).
- 3. J. G. A. Aw, S. W. Lim, J. X. Wang, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan, Y. Wan. Determination of isoform-specific RNA structure with nanopore long reads. Nature Biotechnology. (2021).
- 4. A. S. L. Tay*, **C. Li***, T. Nandi*, ..., N. Nagarajan, J. Common. Atopic dermatitis microbiomes stratifiy into ecological dermotypes enabling microbial virulence and disease severity. **The Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology**. (2021)
- 5. K. R. Chng, T. Ghosh, Y. H. Tan, T. Nandi, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Metagenome-wide association analysis identifies microbial determinants of post-antibiotic ecological recovery in the gut. Nature Ecology and Evolution. (2020).
- 6. K. R. Chng*, **C. Li***, D. Bertrand*, ..., N. Nagarajan. A cartography of opportunistic pathogens and antibiotic-resistance genes in a tertiary hospital environment. **Nature Medicine**. (2020).
- 7. **C.** Li*, K. R. Chng, T. V. Av-Shalom, ..., N. Nagarajan. An expectation-maximization algorithm enables accurate ecological modeling using longitudinal microbiome sequencing data. **Microbiome**. (2019).
- 8. D. Bertrand, J. Shaw, M. Narayan, A. H. Q. Ng, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Nanopore sequencing enables high-resolution analysis of resistance determinants and mobile elements in the human gut microbiome. Nature Biotechnology. (2019).
- 9. D. Bertrand, S. Drissler, B. Chia, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. ConsensusDriver improves upon individual algorithms for predicting driver alterations in different cancer types and individual patients A Toolbox For Precision Oncology. Cancer Research. (2018).
- Y. O. Zhu, P. P. K. Aw, P. F. de Sessions, ..., C. Li, ..., M. Hibberd. Single-virion sequencing of lamivudine-treated HBV populations reveal population evolution dynamics and demographic history. BMC Genomics. (2017).
- 11. K. M. K. Lim, C. Li, K. R. Chng, N. Nagarajan. @MInter: Automated text-mining of microbial interactions. Bioinformatics. (2016).
- 12. K. R. Chng, S. H. Chan, ..., C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Tissue microbiome profiling identifies an enrichment of specific enteric bacteria in *Opisthorchis viverrini* associated cholangiocarcinoma. EBioMedicine. (2016).
- 13. K. R. Chng, A. S. L. Tay, C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Whole metagenome profiling reveals skin

- microbiome dependent susceptibility to atopic dermatitis flares. **Nature Microbiology**. (2016).
- 14. **C. Li***, K. R. Chng, K. M. K. Lim, N. Nagarajan. Predicting Microbial Interactions through Computational Approaches. **Methods**. (2016).
- 15. **C.** Li*, K. R. Chng*, E. J. H. Boey, ..., N. Nagarajan. INC-Seq: Accurate single molecule reads using nanopore sequencing. **GigaScience**. (2016).
- 16. G. Wu, H. Zhao, C. Li, ..., N. Nagarajan. Genus-wide comparative genomics of Malassezia delineates its phylogeny, physiology, and niche adaptation on human skin. PLOS Genetics. (2015).
- 17. A. D. Ewing, *et al.* Combining tumor genome simulation with crowdsourcing to benchmark somatic single-nucleotide-variant detection. **Nature Methods**. (2015). (DREAM Challenge team Lofreq).

Teaching experience

Teaching assistant for CS1010X (Programming Methodology)

National University of Singapore

Jan 2018 – Jun 2018

Teaching assistant for LSM2241 (Introduction to Bioinformatics)

National University of Singapore

Aug 2013 – *Dec* 2013

Talks

 System Biology Modeling with Compositional Microbiome Data Reveals Personalized Gut Microbial Dynamics and Keystone Species. International Human Microbiome Congress 2018, Ireland.

Academic Service

o Ad hoc reviewer for Bioinformatics, GigaScience, Nature Methods, PeerJ, Scientific Reports

References

Niranjan Nagarajan

nagarajann@gis.a-star.edu.sg

Associate Director and Senior Group Leader, Genome Institute of Singapore

Limsoon Wong

limsoon@nus.edu.sg

Kwan-Im-Thong-Hood-Cho-Temple Chair Professor of Computer Science, National University of Singapore

Greg Tucker-Kellogg

dbsgtk@nus.edu.sg

Professor in Practice, Department of Biological Sciences, National University of Singapore